Appleton Sturgis papers, 1862-1874 1997ms469
University of Kentucky Special Collections
- Letter to Captain Russell Sturgis, aboard the Achilles, White House, VA., 1862 June 1 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  To Father. Sturgis engaged another two men to replace the ones that left but still needs a deckhand and engineer. The crew is well and satisfied, and the cooks are clean and use up the stores efficiently. Sturgis thinks they will be staying until Richmond is taken and then ordered up the James River. He has decided to wait on the third certificate, since the ship may be sent home. The decks of the ship began to open from the heat and had to be varnished. Sturgis expects a great battle will soon commence, based on the amount of wounded men coming in every hour.
- Letter to Captain Russell Sturgis, aboard the Achilles, White House, VA., 1862 June 5 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  To Father. The Achilles has been idle in the river, occasionally running to Cumberland, West Point, and Yorktown. Captain Andrews wants the ship to continue working throughout the summer. Sturgis has fallen ill, but will send a memorandum of May expenses soon. Provides a list of amounts paid to dismissed men, amounts he paid to others, and will send a list of the current crew later. Inquires about the money for the second certificate.
- Letter to Margaret Sturgis, aboard the North Star, Baton Rouge, LA., 1862 December 18-19 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  To Mother. December 18: General Banks and staff entered the steamer to go up to the city. General Banks appointed to succeed General Butler. When they reached the levee Lieutenant Hill received orders to establish a depot at Baton Rouge, and ordered to take possession of the Ordinance Office. Sturgis visited the new St. Charles Hotel, and later met with with Colonel Chickering to volunteer for the 1st Massachusett. He describes his uniform and what occured during drill. Illustrated map of the area near Baton Rouge where the battle field was located. December 19: Sturgis was kept awake with false alarms throughout the night and describes sleeping in the field. The Pocahontas arrived with stores and horses.
- Letter to Margaret Sturgis, Ordinance Office, New Orleans, LA., 1863 January 1-2 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  To Mother. Sturgis returned to New Orleans from Baton Rouge, and will now take up duties at the Ordinance Office for the Headquarters of the Department of the Gulf. Discusses money and his expenditures, and asks his mother to send clothing, describing in detail what she should send and what the the clothes should look like. Gives opinions on the importance of the Union Depot in New Orleans, and other stations that have been established. Writes about daily duties, and gives a map of the medical director’s office.
- Letter to Margaret Sturgis, Ordinance Office, New Orleans, LA., 1863 January 5-6 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  To Mother. January 5: Sturgis gives a detailed account of the battle at Galveston: all the soldiers in the 240th were killed, and the Westfield ran aground and was blown up by the Mary Bradshaw, killing Commander Renshaw and his officers. Sturgis lists the ships lost in the battle and the number of men killed. January 6: The Ordinance Office was nearly blown up the previous night. Sturgis describes how the plot to destroy it was discovered and foiled. Sturgis provides drawing of store room area; explains what weaponry was there and its value; and describes how the bomb was made.
- Letter to Margaret Sturgis, Ordinance Office, New Orleans, LA., 1863 January 13 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  To Mother. Sturgis dismissed some staff after the near explosion, has taken sole charge of the storehouse, and describes the difficulty of running it. Received telegrams from Brunswick Bay requesting ammunition and thinks there may be an attack soon. General McClellan has been appointed to command. Sturgis requests to be sent maps of Port Hudson, Vicksburg, and Mobile. Describes how scraps of paper and torn bill are passing for money.
- Letter to Margaret Sturgis, Ordinance Office, New Orleans, LA., 1863 January 19th (Box 1, Folder 42)
  To Mother. General Weitzel has advanced on the 13th from Brunswick Bay to find out confederate whereabouts and destroy the gunboat Cotton. General Emery’s division under orders to move out, and Sturgis gives an account of what the army is doing. Sturgis describes the difference between General Banks and General Butler and complains about the high cost of goods in the south. The Sparkling Sea went ashore on the reefs of Florida. Rumors that the rebel ship Alabama captured the union ship Roanoke. Sturgis is rooming in a house with some soldiers and describes the living situation.
- Letter to Margaret Sturgis, Ordinance Office, New Orleans, LA., 1863 January 24-27; Page one of the letter is covered in a mylar sleeve due to poor condition and some disintegration. (Box 1, Folder 43)
  To Mother. January 24: Sturgis requests to be sent military style clothing for work and a number of other items, describing in detail what the uniform should look like, down to the details on the buttons. Provides a lists the names of the officers he is living with and transcribes a verse of the song Bonnie Blue Flag. Sturgis describes his dislike for General Sherman's character when the general visits the Ordinance Office, and quotes what General Sherman said to him and to Lieutenant Hill. January 27: Sturgis asks to be sent a rubber blanket and leather straps; provides an illustration of a knapsack with straps.
- Letter to Captain Russell Sturgis, Ordinance Office, New Orleans, LA., 1863 February 3 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  To older brother, Russ. The department has been busy, and officers are coming and going all the time with requisitions, invoices, and receipts. Sturgis describes what they do in the office. Received a request from Ship Island for supplies, and Sturgis went aboard the Hartford to see Admiral Faragut (sic. Farragut) for approval of the request. Sturgis describes sitting and drinking with the admiral, and his own impressions. Upon his return to the office, Stugis sees a lady with a counterfeit five dollar bill.
- Letter to Captain Russell Sturgis, Ordinance Office, New Orleans, LA., 1863 February 6 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  To Father. Received a letter from the Adjunct saying that the regiment is encamped two miles from where Sturgis left them on the road, and expecting an attack from the rebels. Arrested a group of young rebels and took action against confederate sympathizers. Lost the Sparkling Sea on the shores of Florida, and have fortified the city as a result.
- Letter to Margaret Sturgis, Ordinance Office, New Orleans, LA., 1863 February 12 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  To Mother. Sturgis describes the discouraging news they received from the North. Burnside may have resigned, Porter was dismissed, and Sumner and Franklin were removed from the army. Sturgis discusses the government's current state of affairs, and his own predictions of what will happen politically and who should be placed where. General Emery is on an expedition, and General Weitzel was last heard to be going through Berwick Bay on the way to Donaldsville. A siege train is being armed, and Sturgis describes the cargo it is taking. The men Sturgis lives with had a stag party at the house and he describes what they did.
- Letter to Margaret Sturgis, Ordinance Office, New Orleans, LA., 1863 February 20 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  To Mother. Sturgis describes mail and mail travel and the return of General Emery’s expedition. There is discord in the city from the lack of discipline on the part of General Banks, and had difficulty keeping the rebel citizens in line during a prisoner exchange at the levee. Sturgis writes about his opinions of slaves and darkeys, the treatment of black officers and the hard feelings between them and the white officers. The rebels attempted another bombing, this time in the navy, but failed.
- Letter to Captain Russell Sturgis, Ordinance Office, New Orleans, LA., 1863 February 26 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  To Father. Mail steamer Ella Warley was lost, but the Roanoke arrived. Sturgis tells his father why he will not accept an oppointment to supervise a black officer regiment, and explains his reasoning. Gives an account of the Billinghurst and Regina Gunn, it's ability to fire 25 rounds 16 times per minute, and what they will do when they receive the gun. Lieutenant Mumford was assigned demonstrate the gun a trial. The Captain of the Laurel Hill played a prank on the rebels who were crowded on the ship and Sturgis describes what happened.
- Letter to Margaret Sturgis, Ordinance Office, New Orleans, LA., 1863 March 3-4; The first and last pages of the letter are covered in mylar sleeves due to poor condition and some disintegration. (Box 1, Folder 49)
  To Mother. Sturgis writes about his work, the dealings he has with other officers, and the levee of ordinance officers from all over came to the department. Orders from General Banks for the 18th N.Y. Batt. to leave for Baton Rouge, along with two others. Sturgis does not think the Union will be able to hold Baton Rouge, the rebels having captured two of the union's best gunboats: Queen of the West and Indianola. The rebels have four or five ironclads which could drive out the fleet at Port Hudson. Sturgis discusses battle scenarios, soldiers, and describes the contents of a package received, comparing what those items would cost in New Orleans.
- Letter to Margaret Sturgis, Ordinance Office, New Orleans, LA., 1863 March 7 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  To Mother. Sturgis thinks this will be his farewell letter from New Orleans. The Union is planning to lay siege to Fort Hudson, and General Grover was in the city to consult with General Banks, General Sherman, and General Emery. Sturgis discusses the possibilities of battle, and various outcomes that may occur. Plans on leaving by boat on Tuesday or Thursday.
- Letter to Margaret Sturgis, between Port Hudson and Baton Rogue, LA., 1863 March 14 (Box 1, Folder 51)
  To Mother. The army is advancing to draw the fire from the field battalions, and to distract the rebels. Sturgis is with a section of the 18th Batt. They were ordered to hold their place as long as possible, and then retreat to town.
- Letter to Margaret Sturgis, Ordinance Office, New Orleans, LA., 1863 March 19; The first page and the last two pages of the letter are covered in mylar sleeves due to poor condition and some disintegration. (Box 1, Folder 52)
  To Mother. Sturgis has returned from Baton Rouge, and responds to his mother’s inquiry about the shooting of General Banks. Describes army movements and strategies concerning the 41st Massachusetts, 173rd and 175th New York, 18th N.Y. Batt., 12th Massachusetts, 21st Indiana siege train, and 3rd Louisiana. Helped perform a review and inspection of troops, and describes the landscape he saw while out riding. Sturgis acted as Chief Commissioner during review of the 18th Battalion, and was later fired upon by rebels after discovering pickets. Provides illustrated map of the roads he travelled on. Sturgis witnesses rebels using lights in their houses to send signals to one another, and describes altercation he had in one particular house. Receives letter from Lt. Hill to return and learns that the Mississippi was destroyed.
- Letter to Margaret Sturgis, New Orleans, LA., 1863 April 3 (Box 1, Folder 53)
  To Mother. Sturgis writes that he has been very ill with acclimating fever.
- Letter to Margaret Sturgis, Ordinance Office, New Orleans, LA., 1863 April 8 (Box 1, Folder 54)
  To Mother. Sturgis describes the recovery from his illness, the doctors he saw, and the treatments he received. Met the Assistant Surgeon USQ and Assistant Chief Medical Director. The army has been away from Baton Rouge, General Banks has taken to the field again, and the Union lost another gunboat.
- Letter to Captain Russell Sturgis, New Orleans, LA., 1863 April 13 (Box 1, Folder 55)
  To Father. Sturgis writes about his endeavor to gain a charter with Colonel Shipley, and describes the comings and goings of the ships in New Orleans. Hopes to keep the Thames employed by the Navy and has been looking for housing for the Achilles to do work. Gives details of what they might be able to do with the Achilles.
- Letter to Margaret Sturgis, New Orleans, LA., 1863 April 15 (Box 1, Folder 56)
  To Mother. The top of the first page has a drawing with hands pointing at the word Private. Sturgis has taken a holiday from the office due to a relapse with his illness, and is receiving a tonic of port wine, wild cherry bark, and some other substance. Requests that his mother to send him port wine and sherry for medicine. He also describes using homeopathy prescribed by Mrs. Russell, and a staphysagria medicine. Mentions the Thames had an accident.
- Letter to Margaret Sturgis, New Orleans, LA., 1863 April 21-22 (Box 1, Folder 57)
  To Mother. April 21: The words Read to yourself are written at the top of the letter. Sturgis writes that he has a fever, and mentions the current treatments he is taking. Lieutenant Mumford and Sturgis purchased a case of wine from a merchant, and Sturgis lists types of wine he currently has and how he uses them for his illness. April 22: Sturgis describes how General Banks has almost succeeded in cutting the rebel line of supplies, and is currently heading towards Alexandria on the Red River. General Banks may starve out Port Hudson and Vicksburg in 4 months. General Sherman was ordered to sieze all private horse equipment, and is currently sending it to the depot's storehouses in New Orleans.
- Letter to Captain Russell Sturgis, New Orleans, LA., 1863 April 24 (Box 1, Folder 58)
  To Father. Sturgis has made several inquiries about towing business in New Orleans, and explains how it is different there than it is in New York. One line of boats belongs to Stanton and Co., a rebel company. Discusses quality of other boats, their rates for towing, and official dealings of the ships. Unable to find safe housing for the Achilles and suggests to his father to consider selling it. Mentions General Banks and the rebels, and how they were expecting an attack that never came.
- Letter to Margaret Sturgis, New Orleans, LA., 1863 April 28-29 (Box 1, Folder 59)
  To Mother. April 28: The illness prevented Sturgis from going with Banks on an expedition. Queen of the West was blown up when the gunboat Calhoun fired upon it. Captain Shunk returned to the office, and Lieutenant Hill has gone to take the captain’s place. Sturgis changed rooms in the boarding house and provides an illustration of the layout of the new room. April 29: Sturgis asks his mother to remember him to Miss Gardener from Elm City, gives details about clothes, and asks for a steel collar.
- Letter to Margaret Sturgis, Ordinance Office, New Orleans, LA., 1863 April 29 (Box 1, Folder 60)
  To Mother. The word Private is written at the top of the letter. Sturgis responds to his mother’s inquiries for him to come home, and does not think it right to go home while the war is still going on. Older brother Russell just settled into business, and brother Ed is still too young, so Sturgis feels this is his duty. Discusses possibility of yellow fever in summer. The rebels are evacuating Port Hudson, and Banks may move his army across Baton Rouge to follow them.
- Letter to Margaret Sturgis, Ordinance Office, New Orleans, LA., 1863 May 5-15 (Box 1, Folder 61)
  To Mother. May 5: Sturgis was promoted to Chief temporarily. Writes about the slowness of the mail, and the lack of steamers. General Grant is sending about 2000 men, and General Hunter will send 5000, along with several ironclads. Lieutenant Mumford resigned and went home. Sturgis met a Mrs. Richards, friend of Miss Betsy Sturgis. Asks for mother to send Harpers Weekly. May 15: Sturgis expresses his desire to fight in the army on the Potomac when General McClullen returns and tells his mother to remember him on June 2nd for his 21st birthday.
- Letter to Margaret Sturgis, Ordinance Office, New Orleans, LA., 1863 May 20 (Box 1, Folder 62)
  To Mother. The office has been slow, and Sturgis writes that he has been bored. Sturgis thinks Port Hudson will likely fall within the week. General Banks has been crossing a force towards Bayou Lara, while General Anges will advance from Baton Rouge, and General Grant is within 50 miles of the city. Relays news that there are 1000 rebels at Port Hudson and the railroad line was cut from Clinton. Sturgis expresses concern that New Orleans has less than 5000 troops in the city, since most have been sent to battle.
- Letter to Margaret Sturgis, 19th Army Corps, New Orleans, LA., 1863 May 26 (Box 1, Folder 63)
  To Mother. Captain Shunk went to Brasheirs, leaving Sturgis in charge. He received a package from home, with what the southerners call Yankee Sugas, clothes, socks, and a steel collar, which Sturgis describes in detail. Visited Mrs. Russell and gave her a pistol. Lack of news from Port Hudson, and thinks the road to Vicksburg will open up by June 1st. General Banks is at Baton Rouge but doesn’t have enough men to hold it. Colonel Chickering and his force were attacked and pushed back to Franklin.
- Letter to Margaret Sturgis, aboard the Besbille, travelling towards Port Hudson, LA., 1863 May 30 (Box 1, Folder 64)
  To Mother. Sturgis asks for his mother to let Mrs. Balatine know he will be going to the front. Sturgis is on the way to Port Hudson, and only given 20 minutes to pack. He will go to Springfield Landing and from there on to the front.
- Letter to Margaret Sturgis, on the battle front, Port Hudson, LA., 1863 June 8; Letter is covered in a mylar sleeve due to poor condition and some disintegration. (Box 1, Folder 65)
  To Mother. Sturgis was assigned as acting aid to General H.E. Pain, and has been with him nearly a week, and just returned that morning from an expedition to Clinton, trying to catch rebels who drove Colonel Greisson into an ambush. He describes the expedition, the loss of 200 men to sunstroke, and the burning of Clinton. They have been under sharpshooter fire several times while carrying out orders, and a ball broke one of the spurs on his new horse.
- Letter to Margaret Sturgis, 3rd Division of the 19th Army Corps, Port Hudson, LA., 1863 June 15 (Box 1, Folder 66)
  To Mother. Sturgis is in a hospital bed in the tent of Captain Porter, Chief Q.M. to the division. He was shot in the right leg the day before during a battle he fought in along with General Pain’s division. General Pain and Lt. Pearce fell as well. Sturgis gives details about his injury and the battle. Believes he will be sent down to New Orleans in a few days. Describes the current battle going on, how they are being attacked in the rear by 4000, General Weitzel's march out into battle, and the truce that was refused by General Gardener.
- Letter to Captain Russell Sturgis, Officer's Hospital, Baton Rogue, LA., 1863 June 25 (Box 1, Folder 67)
  To Father. Sturgis describes his current health, the battle at Port Hudson, and the loss of troops. His division lost 823 men. Plans to stay with Mrs. Ropers as soon as possible and will return home from there. Writes about expenses he has accrued and asks for help to pay them.
- Letter to Margaret Sturgis, Officer's Hospital, Baton Rogue, LA, 1863 June 27-29 (Box 1, Folder 68)
  To Mother. Describes the appearance of the Hotel de Fonlie; what other patients are like; daily routine and life in the ward; and the continued fighting at Port Hudson. Gives his opinions about General Banks and the war, General Sherman’s protest, and the many failing of the siege attempt. Provides a detailed account of what he was doing after leaving New Orleans; his time on the front; the battle; meeting General Paine and his staff; his injury; and being pulled off the field by men from the 38th Massachusetts.
- Letter to Margaret Sturgis, New Orleans, LA., 1863 July 6 (Box 1, Folder 69)
  To Mother. Sturgis thinks he looks like a mummy, and describes the ice treatments to his leg, the kinds of meals they serve, and how he is being cared for. He was visited by the District Attorney, Mr. Whaples, along with his wife. Gives details of his journey on the steamer that brought him to New Orleans. During the passage Sturgis saw the aftermath of the battle at Donaldsville. He discusses possible strategies the Confederates might use to take New Orleans and what kind of response strategy the Union would have.
- Letter to Captain Russell Sturgis, New Orleans, LA., 1863 July 7 (Box 1, Folder 70)
  To Father. Sturgis responds to his father about business matters, his impending passage home, medical treatments he is taking, and describes how he is being cared for.
- Letter to Margaret Sturgis, New Orleans, LA., 1863 July 14 (Box 1, Folder 71)
  To Mother. Sturgis intends to leave on the steamer Columbia between the 19th and 21st of July and thinks he will reach New York by the 28th of July. Describes the doctor’s opinion on his health for travel, settling debts, and things he must do to prepare for his departure. General Sherman is to travel north on the Columbia with Sturgis, since the general was badly injured in battle. Sturgis describes visits with different generals and officers to obtain a pass to leave.
- General Release: Appleton Sturgis, Russell Sturgis, and Albert M. Da Costa, 1874 May 9; Document is covered in a mylar sleeve due to poor condition and some disintegration. (Box 1, Folder 72)
  Official document regarding Appleton Sturgis, on behalf of Russell Sturgis, and Albert M. Da Costa, for money paid in the amount of $643.10 from Sturgis to Da Costa, absolving Sturgis of any claim made by Da Costa concerning commission owed him for steamship Teazer. Witnesses are Da Costa and John Cropper, Notary Public.